Good morning. Today's דף daf is ו. vav. And we pick up
at the two dots about eight lines in. And we have spent
the first four דף daf talking about the source for the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol and possibly in parallel, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, possibly in parallel the כהן Kohen who
did the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, the source for the idea of
a seven-day separation. And we had developed basically two models, that of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who learned it out from the מלואים Miluim
and that of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who learned it out from
הר סיני. Har Sinai. And then we had a little bit of
a digression around the מלואים Miluim and exactly how the מלואים Miluim
took place and what was מעכב. me'akev. So now the גמרא Gemara
in a way doubles back and reopens the conversation. So again, it's
about eight lines from the top on ו עמוד א, vav amud
aleph, five with the two dots.
מפרישין כהן גדול מביתו. Mafrishin Kohen Gadol mibeto. So you would separate
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol from his house for seven days prior
to the עבודה avoda on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and he would
live in this לשכת פרהדרין, Lishkat Parhedrin, in this chamber in the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So the גמרא Gemara says, למה מפרישין? lama
mafrishin? Why do we separate? It says, למה מפרישין, lama mafrishin, why
do we separate him? כדקאמרן, kideka'amarnan, weren't you paying attention? Like we
said before, אי רבי יוחנן כדית ליה, ei Rabbi Yochanan kedislei, weren't
you paying attention with mine? אי רבי יוחנן כדית ליה, ei Rabbi
Yochanan kedislei, אי ריש לקיש כדית ליה. ei Reish Lakish kedislei. Either
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan for the reason he says or ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish for the reason he says. So it's like what we've
just been discussing for the last four days. It's either about the
idea of מלואים Miluim or it's
about הר סיני. Har Sinai. So what do you mean why do
we separate? אלא הכי קאמר, ela haki kama, this is what it
means.
מביתו למה פירש? mibeto lama perish? So we got the מפרישין כהן
גדול, Mafrishin Kohen Gadol, the first three words of the משנה Mishna
or whatever, the first three words we explained. It's either based on
הר סיני Har Sinai or based on the מלואים. Miluim. But the
question is the next word, מביתו, mibeto, which ביתו beto does not
just mean his physical house and that he would live in the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but ביתו זו אשתו, beto zu ishto, you
know, as is a very common way not just in terms of
interpreting the פסוק pasuk by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, וכפר בעדו ובעד
ביתו, vechiper ba'ado uve'ad beto, which גמרא Gemara says ביתו
זו אשתו, beto zu ishto, which is why he has to be
married on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but
also throughout the גמרא, Gemara, throughout ש"ס, Shas, בית bayit is really
a very common way that the גמרא Gemara refers
to a man's wife, like actually ארמית Aramaic words for wife is
דביתיהו, devataiyu, the בית bayit of so and so. You know, so
that obviously reflects certain type of a perspective on women and wives,
but the גמרא Gemara here is taking it for granted that the
word in the משנה Mishna why did they separate him from his
house meant his wife. That he didn't live with his wife for
seven days. Why not?
That's answer two.
Alright, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says why couldn't his
wife come and live with him there in this לשכת פרהדרין? Lishkat
Parhedrin? Why not? So let's take a look.
תניא, Tanya, רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer,
שמא תמצא אשתו ספק נדה ויבוא עליה. shema timatze ishto safek nida
veyavo aleha. No, it's a טומאה tumah concern. It's not the מלואים
Miluim concern, it's not the הר סיני Har Sinai issue, which is
fascinating because you could have said as Hanoch Michael's דעה de'ah to
say, that that's exactly part of the point of מלואים Miluim and
הר סיני. Har Sinai. Fascinatingly the גמרא Gemara does not understand that
to be necessary. And says no, it's because of a טומאה tumah
concern. We need him to be טהור tahor on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and if his wife is there with him and they are
sleeping together and they're having sex, then maybe she will be a
ספק נדה safek nida and he'll have sex with her. I mean
presumably wouldn't have sex with her if she definitely a נדה nida
but okay and then he'll be טמא tamei because a man who
has sex with a woman who's a נדה nida besides the fact
that it's one of the forbidden acts of sex and you're חייב
כרת, chayav karet, it also makes the man טמא tamei with a
טומאה tumah of seven days like the טומאה tumah of נדה. nida.
So that's why, because we want to avoid another way of avoiding
טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא Gemara first says one minute, אטו ברשיעי
עסקינן? atu bersha'ei askinan? One minute, are we talking about evil people?
I mean he would never would
knowingly, consciously have sex with his wife not only when she's a
נדה nida but even when she's a ספק נדה. safek nida. He's
not going to do that. I mean just because of the prohibition
not even because of the טומאה. tumah. אלא שמא יבוא על אשתו
ותמצא ספק נדה. ela shema yavo al ishto vetimsa safek nida. No,
here's the problem that he'll have sex with his wife permissibly but
then what will happen after they've had sex she'll realize that she'll
find a stain on the bed and the ספק safek but the
ספק safek will be after not before. So the act of having
sex will be what? Why is it ספק? safek?
Yeah why the whole language of ספק safek is problematic?
Well right so I it could have said תמצא נדה timsa nida
but again I want to describe I
think alright I think it wants to describe a scenario that maybe
is like you know a little bit more likely like if it
turns out that she knows she's bleeding while they're having sex you
know the גמרא Gemara talks about an obligation of husband and wife
to separate עת וסתה eis vestah at the time when she's expected
to get her period and presumably you know the גמרא Gemara would
I think would assume that he would keep that as well. Possible
that this wasn't when she was expected to get her period, but
she got her period nevertheless. But okay, I think what the גמרא
Gemorah wants to describe is a scenario that might be a little
bit more common. You know, they have sex, no problem, whatever, and
then an hour later she finds she you know she sees that
there's a spot of blood on the sheets. And now we have
a whole question, was he you know was he טמא tamei or
not? Was she a נדה niddah when they were having sex or
not?
So, but
you're right, it could have said, I will get back to you,
it could have said that תמצא נדה timatzeh niddah but I think
it's just doing ספק נדה safek niddah to make it a little
a little maybe more realistic. So אמרו רבנן קמי דרב חסדא. amru
rabanan kammai d'Rav Chisda. So the rabbis said this to רב חסדא
Rav Chisda that that was the concern, that he would wind up
becoming טמא tamei if he was living with his wife in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and having sex. So the גמרא Gemorah says
כמאן? keman? That's what רב חסדא Rav Chisda said back, כמאן כרבי
עקיבא. keman k'Rabbi Akiva. This would only be a legitimate concern according
to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva דאמר נדה מטמאה בועלה, d'amar niddah metama
bo'alah,
that the נדה niddah makes her husband טמא. tamei. Now the Torah
says the נדה niddah makes her husband טמא, tamei, but I'll explain
this in a minute. כי רבנן האמרי אין נדה מטמאה בועלה, ki
rabanan ha'amri ein niddah metama bo'alah, the נדה niddah doesn't make her
husband טמא. tamei.
Now again, this does not mean that if a woman is definitely
a נדה niddah and she has sex with her husband that her
husband is not טמא. tamei. It means retroactively. No, the keyword that's
missing and implied here is retroactively. The first משנה Mishna in נדה
Niddah says that if a woman finds
blood, either through an internal check or on her garments that she
knows came from her and did not come from another source and
so on, then now she doesn't know exactly when the bleeding began.
I mean even if it's an internal check, הלכתית halachically a woman
is a נדה niddah when the blood exits the
uterus and through the cervix and goes into the vaginal canal even
before it comes out of the body. So if a woman finds
blood, she doesn't know when she became a נדה. niddah. So the
first משנה Mishna in נדה Niddah says, that's a debate of בית
שמאי ובית הלל Beis Shammai u'Beis Hillel actually, here בית הלל Beis
Hillel is more lenient. Anyway, but basically, and then there's the position
of the חכמים Chachamim and the basic position of the first משנה,
Mishna, I say בית שמאי Beis Shammai is more lenient, like I
said. The first position anyway, the position of the חכמים Chachamim is
that she is טמאה tmeiah retroactively for the last 24 hours, unless
she did an internal check prior, and then obviously it would be
the lesser of the two. Okay, but assuming she didn't do a
recent internal check, she's טמאה tmeiah 24 hours retroactively. But what about,
that's in terms of if she handled objects and she touched תרומה
terumah and so on, we say it became טמא, tamei, anything she
handled in the last 24 hours. What if she had sex with
her husband in the last 24 hours? So there the חכמים Chachamim
say, okay, that far we're not going to go, you know. Anyway
what would happen, everybody would be anxious having sex, because if my
wife finds finds within the next 24 hours right that she's a
נדה, niddah, and if I find out in the next 24 hours
I'm a you know I'm a נדה, niddah, then I'm going to
have to think that this act of sex was being done, you
know we were transgressing. So that's my psychological explanation. But whatever the
reason is, the גמרא Gemorah says that according to the חכמים Chachamim
this 24 hours retroactive would not would not define her husband as
being טמא tamei for having had sex with a נדה. niddah. Only
things that she handled. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagrees. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says that even the husband would be טמא tamei 24
hours prior. So the גמרא Gemorah is saying, you just described that
the scenario you're concerned with, as everybody here said, why don't we
just say the scenario that she was bleeding she started bleeding as
they were having sex? But again, the גמרא Gemorah I think wanted
to give a little more common scenario, that she she thought she
was bleeding a few hours within a day after they had sex.
Gemara says fine, but that wouldn't have made the husband, the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, טמא, tamei, only according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
According to the חכמים, Chachamim, it wouldn't have made him טמא. tamei.
So what's the concern? So let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemorah says אמרו ליה לרב חסדא. amru lei l'Rav Chisda. So that's
what the rabbis said to רב חסדא Rav Chisda when they were
discussing this topic. So אמר להו רב חסדא. amar lehu Rav Chisda.
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda responded back to them and said, no,
אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu teima rabanan, it can even be the rabbis
that say you do not retroactively 24 hours consider the husband you
know that if they've had sex the husband is טמא. tamei. But
nevertheless, עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי עקיבא ad kan lo
palgi rabanan alei d'Rabbi Akiva אלא באחר אחר, ela b'achar achar, only
after the after. אבל בחד אחר aval b'chad achar מודו ליה, modu
lei, he would agree.
Which basically
means, it's very precise, it's funny, but which basically means, how soon
after they had sex did you find did she find that she
was bleeding? So the גמרא Gemorah there has has basically three time
periods. One is basically the second that they separated. She did an
internal check and she saw she was bleeding. That the גמרא Gemorah
says you have to assume that she was a נדה niddah at
the time of sex and that even impacts the obligation to bring
a קרבן korban for having had sex, knowing it's assuming definitely that
they've had sex when she was a נדה. niddah. Then there's this
middle stage, which is which is the time it takes to get
off of the bed and to basically and to do a rinse
and to do an internal rinse. So let's say that's you know
the 30 seconds, okay, whatever it is. So if it's not one
second after, it's between one second and 30 seconds, then then it's
a ספק safek whether she was a נדה niddah when they were
having sex. So it has implications for קרבן korban and everybody would...
Agree the husband is טמא tamei because it's a real ספק, safek,
it's a genuine biblical ספק safek if she finds that she's bleeding
within the next thirty seconds. Any time that's אחר, acher, that's after
they had sex. If that's one אחר, acher, then everybody agrees. But
אחר דאחר, acher de'acher, after that אחר, acher, after that thirty seconds,
that's where there's the debate. That's where everybody agrees it's only a
rabbinic concern retrospective, retroactive to assume that it was happening when they
were having sex, and the Rabbis say it does not apply to
the husband and Rabbi עקיבא Akiva says it would extend to the
husband. So, there is a time period after sex where, again, could
have just said during sex, she found she's a נדה, niddah, but
there's a time period after that everybody agrees finding that she's bleeding
would
make us have to be worried that they were having sex when
she was a נדה, niddah, would have us worry that even at
a biblical level that the husband is טמא. tamei. If it was
after the after, after thirty seconds, then it's true not everybody agrees
the husband would have to worry. So, that's how the גמרא Gemara
describes what the concern is. Now, we need to stop here and
ask two questions.
First question is which Michael asks, which is an excellent question which
I don't have a good answer to, which is: Why does it
have to be a, if I would say, a more secondary concern
of טומאה? tumah? Wouldn't you have thought conceptually the idea of separating
based on the model of הר סיני Har Sinai or based on
the model
of the כהן kohen preparing, you know, of the מלואים miluim would
include sort of almost like leaving the physical world behind? Now, there
might be a difference between the מלואים miluim model and the הר
סיני Har Sinai model. You could easily have said, although the מלואים
miluim model is מפתח אהל מועד לא תצאו שבעת ימים פן תמותו,
mipetach ohel moed lo teitzu shivat yamim pen tamutu, that they really
had to stay in that environment, but it might not so much
have been to like emphasize the spiritual over the physical. It might
have been like a full immersion into the life of the כהונה
kehunah and into the life of the משכן Mishkan and the עבודה
avoda *avodah* of the משכן. And as we spoke about, מלואים miluim
is really about initiating them into the service of the כהונה, kehunah,
initiating the first use of the space, initiating their role as כהנים,
kohanim, you know, as I mentioned to you the other day, the
Rav said that by יום כיפור Yom Kippur translates as the idea
of sort of imparting upon him with a special status of a
כהן גדול. kohen gadol. But it's not about becoming, you know, sort
of like I said, shedding your material self, it's about immersing yourself
into this new role in order to allow that role to take
place, to give you that status and so on. So that, one
minute, so that you could have said fine, so take your wives
with you, why not sleep with your wives at night, right? You're
still immersing yourself in this role as a כהן kohen or as
a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. But the הר סיני Har Sinai model
I have to tell you is harder. I mean, my god, the
הר סיני, Har Sinai, what did we say? It starts, we said
it was the six days prior to or the six first six
days of the forty days. What do we know about the forty
days? It says, לחם לא אכלתי ומים לא שתיתי, lachem lo achalti
umayim lo shatiti, right?
He didn't even eat any food or water. I mean, the גמרא
Gemara even says that maybe the first days was to cleanse him
of all of these, you know, of all of his food. רש״י
Rashi says okay, then that wouldn't be the model because we don't
say the כהן גדול kohen gadol has to starve the seven days
or six days prior. But nevertheless, it certainly seems like ושם עם
ה׳, v'sham im Hashem, that the emphasis there is, you know, separate
from your wives. We know three days prior to הר סיני, Har
Sinai, היו נכונים לשלשת ימים אל תגשו אל אשה. heyu nechonim lishloshet
yamim al tigshu el isha. And the Rabbis try to say that
that actually, you read that to say because that really emphasizes of
course the men at הר סיני Har Sinai and not the women,
and it's interesting that the Rabbis reread that to say the concern
was that the women shouldn't be טמאה tmeiah because they'd recently had
sex with their husbands. But the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim
is, you know, this separation. And when the תורה Torah says לך
אמר להם שובו לכם לאהליכם ואתה פה עמד עמדי, lech emor lahem
shuvu lachem le’oholeichem ve'ata po amod imadi, right? The classic דרשה, drasha,
again this isn't in the פסוקים, psukim, is go to your אהל,
ohel, means go back to having sex with your wives, but you,
you know, you stay here, you remain, you separate from your wife.
And the whole idea of צפורה Tzipporah and so on and, you
know, how חז״ל Chazal explain what you, you know, about the אשה
כושית, isha Kushit, why was she abandoned by משה Moshe etc. So
I really do not understand according to
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, געזונטהייט, gezuntheit, why we need this additional explanation.
Now, of course the dominant position was רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so
you could say bottom line we're explaining this according to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan the basis of the מלואים. miluim. But according to ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish who bases it on הר סיני, Har Sinai, it
would seem the answer is pretty self-evident and I do not know
why the גמרא Gemara does not offer it. That is issue number
one. Issue number two is: What do you mean, Michael, I was
sorry, I was waiting for you to ask this question, Michael, what
do you mean go take your wife with you and live there
in the לשכת פרהדרין? lishkat parhedrin? Since when can you be having
sex on the grounds of the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? What type
of a הוה אמינא havamina is that? How crazy is that idea,
right? I mean, in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in the עזרה
azarah you're not even allowed to sit. So what type of crazy
thought is this? So what? You were ready to ask that question.
Okay, fine, I'll give you a chance. So let's take a look
at רש״י. Rashi. מבית עולמו פירש, mi-bet-olama peresh, this is like twenty
lines before the lines get wide. Wait for a question before you
answer. All right. מאשתו למה פירש? Mi-eishto lama pirash? Why did he
separate, why separate from your wife? So רש"י Rashi says like this:
מאשתו למה פירש. Mi-eishto lama pirash. תבוא אשתו עמו שם Tavo ishto
imo sham שהרי על כרחך לשכת פרהדרין לא היתה קדושה. sheharei al
korchacha Lishkat Parhedrin lo haysa kedusha. Okay, you have to say that
this does not have the sanctity of the עזרה. Azarah. Remember we
discussed that on the first day, where was it located, where was
the door open into the עזרה, Azarah, into the and maybe only
into the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim and so on. So רש"י Rashi
says however and wherever it was constructed, it could not have been
the קדושה kedusha of the עזרה Azarah proper. Why? So before we
even get to the wife, שאין ישיבה בעזרה אלא למלכי בית דוד
כל שכן שכיבה. she-ein yeshiva ba-Azarah ela le-malchei beis David kol she-kein
shechiva. So רש"י Rashi said how does he go to sleep in
the room? You're not even allowed to sit in the עזרה. Azarah.
So wherever this was built and the גמרא Gemara will discuss like
maybe its door was open, maybe its status is defined not physically
where it is, but which space its door is open into. But
wherever it was built, רש"י Rashi says it cannot have been the
sanctity of the עזרה Azarah because then before you even get to
the issue of sleeping with his wife,
how would he be able to sleep? How would he be able
to lie down? So therefore רש"י Rashi says once it's not in
the עזרה, Azarah, we could also ask let him be there with
his wife, let him sleep with his wife. But of course Michael
says, one minute, you mean to tell me, okay, it doesn't have
the קדושה kedusha of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It has the
קדושה kedusha of the הר הבית. Har Habayis. So still you're allowed
to have sex on הר הבית? Har Habayis? Meaning even if the
act of sex is not itself somehow forbidden, but through the act
of sex the husband becomes a בעל קרי, baal keri, right? He
becomes somebody who has had a seminal emission. So בעל קרי baal
keri isn't allowed on הר הבית. Har Habayis. So תוספות, Tosafot, I
still don't get it. Okay, so let's take a look at תוספות.
Tosafot.
מאשתו למה פירש, Mi-eishto lama pirash, right? I mean just because the
wife is there with him doesn't mean that they're having sex. Of
course.
Okay, so but then so maybe he was
in a situation where he might, why would he do that?
Okay, so you're saying have his wife there and don't have sex
with the guidelines not to have sex. And then there's the regular
guidelines.
All right, okay.
I think the גמרא Gemara never spells that out. When it says
let his wife be with him, I think it assumes as we
see in the next line that at least the question assumes let
them be there and be having and living a normal marital life
and having sex. So the question is why was it
not addressing that issue to begin with? Let's
see תוספות. Tosafot. פירש רש"י Pirash Rashi תבוא אשתו עמו שם Tavo
ishto imo sham שהרי על כרחך לשכת פרהדרין לא היתה קדושה sheharei
al korchacha Lishkat Parhedrin lo haysa kedusha שאין ישיבה בעזרה כל שכן
שכיבה. she-ein yeshiva ba-Azarah kol she-kein shechiva. וקשה לה Ve-kasha leh דנהי
דלא קדשה קדושת עזרה מכל מקום הר הבית היתה. denahi delo kadesha
kedushat Azarah mikol makom Har Habayis haysa. דתניא בפרק בחצות De-tanya be-perek
Bachatzot כל הר הבית מחנה לוייה הוא kol Har Habayis machaneh Leviyah
hu ובעל קרי אינו נכנס במחנה לוייה. uve-baal keri eino nichnas be-machaneh
Leviyah. So again the גמרא Gemara could have framed the question let
him be there without having sex and then no we're concerned he
still might, okay, but it didn't say that, it didn't frame the
question that way. So what's the assumption that he's having sex? It's
הר הבית. Har Habayis. דאמרינן בפרק אלו דברים De-amrinan be-perek Elu Devarim
זב וכל זב לרבות בעל קרי. Zav ve-chol zav lerabot baal keri.
אלא יש לפרש Ela yesh le-faresh מאשתו למה פירש Mi-eishto lama pirash
הוה לן למימר שיפרישו למחילה אחת בהר הבית. hava lan le-meimar she-yafrishu
le-mechilah achat be-Har Habayis. Maybe he should be staying not in a
chamber on the temple but maybe he should be staying in an
underground tunnel. דאמרינן De-amrinan like they said Kennedy had tunnels for that
reason, right? דאמרינן בפרק כיצד צולין De-amrinan be-perek Ketzad Tzolin דמחילות לא
נתקדשו. de-mechilot lo nitkadshu.
Okay, so according to תוספות Tosafot it's quite fascinating also
because he has a very legitimate question but it's also fascinating when
we think of the question about this idea of פרישה, perishah, right?
Because if תוספות Tosafot says the פרישה perishah is not on the
grounds of not only not on temple grounds not on הר הבית
Har Habayis grounds just underground. But if one of the ideas of
the פרישה perishah is רש לקיש's Resh Lakish's model of נתכסה בענן
and
presumably
you need to somehow be in the presence of the temple not
just in some underground
tunnel, maybe if it's the מילואים model you would think also requires
you to be more on temple or at least on הר הבית
Har Habayis grounds. So in order for תוספות Tosafot to deal with
the הוה אמינא havaminah of going to a tunnel,
it changes our understanding of where the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has
to be when he is being separated. Of course that's the הוה
אמינא. havaminah. At the end of the day his wife isn't with
him so we can go back and assume that he's right there
on temple grounds whether it has the sanctity of הר הבית Har
Habayis or whether it has the sanctity of the עזרה Azarah is
a different question but it's located certainly on הר הבית Har Habayis
and maybe even in the עזרה Azarah space just without the sanctity
of the עזרה Azarah which is an issue we'll get to based
on where it's open to. Yes.
I was thinking about a lot of things before but the problem
with that answer is because then he's focusing on the wrong word
because the גמרא Gemara focused on מפרישין mafrishin as opposed to לשכת
פרהדרין, Lishkat Parhedrin, right? And according to תוספות Tosafot the question should
have been or גמרא's Gemara's question should have been למה לשכת פרהדרין
lama Lishkat Parhedrin should have been למחילה. le-mechilah. Right, right, but the
yeah
no but now he wasn't saying the גמרא Gemara was asking לשכת
פרהדרין. Lishkat Parhedrin. The גמרא Gemara was asking why can't he be
with his wife parenthesis and go somewhere else rather than the לשכת
פרהדרין. Lishkat Parhedrin. But why do we start with the assumption he
can't be with his wife? That's the way the גמרא's Gemara's question
is. So Let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so אמר
רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, so said רב זירא, Rav Zeira, about
again like I don't know twenty lines from the bottom, fifteen lines,
middle of the line, אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, שמע מינה
בא ונידל אינה כנידה וטובל ביום. shema mina ba ve-nidal eina ke-nida
ve-tovel be-yom. From this idea that the concern of separating the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is a concern that he would from his wife
is that he would have had sex with his wife and wound
up having the טומאה tumah of בא ונידל, ba ve-nidal, a man
who has had sex with a נידה, nida, we can see that
the טומאה tumah of a person who has had sex with a
נידה nida is not identical to the טומאה tumah of a נידה.
nida. Although the תורה Torah says ותהי טומאתה עליו, ve-tehi tumatah alav,
that the טומאה tumah of the נידה nida then becomes also the
טומאה tumah of the man, transfers from the woman, not transfers like
it leaves but goes, extends from the woman and applies to the
man, says it’s not exactly identical. In what way is it not
identical? He says וטובל ביום. ve-tovel be-yom. When does a נידה nida
go to the מקווה? mikvah? A נידה nida goes to the מקווה,
mikvah, a woman who is a נידה, nida, I’m sorry I should
say a woman who’s a נידה nida goes to the מקווה mikvah
at night. Okay, now I’m not talking about today's practice, which is
also based on more complicated hybrids and so on, but in the
תורה, Torah, the תורה Torah basically says שבעת ימים תהיה בנדתה, shivat
yamim tihyeh ve-nidatah, okay, that she is, you know, seven days a
נידה, nida, and and then you know at the end, חז"ל Chazal
understood the full seven days and she cannot go to the מקווה
mikvah in the middle of the seventh day, she can only go
to the מקווה mikvah at nightfall. Again, nowadays it's different because nowadays
a woman waits you know till the bleeding stops and then seven
days without bleeding. According to the תורה, Torah, a woman who is
had her menstrual flow just you know starts counting from the day
the flow begins and the assumption,
many מפרשים meforshim say that the reason the תורה Torah assumes she
is טמא tameh seven days is because a menstrual period sometimes obviously
it would be an extreme case could last for up to seven
days so it's assumed that she could be having bleeding throughout those
seven days and then the menstrual period is over and she goes
to the מקווה mikvah a week after the menstruation began. Okay, but
she goes the night of the seventh, she can't go the day
of the seventh. And he's saying from the way you described what
the concern was then I can prove to you that the man
who has had sex with a נידה nida goes the day of
the seventh not the following night. Why? Let's take a look. וטובל
ביום. ve-tovel be-yom. דאמרת de-amarta בא ונידל כנידה, ba ve-nidal ke-nida, if
he has the exact same status as a נידה, nida, אימת טבי?
emat tavi? When would he go to the מקווה? mikvah? דליליה. de-leilya.
He would go at night. So למחר le-machar היכי עביד עבודה? hechi
avid avoda? How could he do the עבודה avodah. the next day
on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? ובעי הערב שמש. ve-baei ha-erev shemesh. He
would need it to be nightfall. Every time after you've gone to
the מקווה mikvah you need the following night to become completely טהור.
tahor. So what does that mean?
It means here is right let's say these are the
seven days, it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah two days okay days of
תשרי, Tishrei, right? 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Okay,
this is יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? So not to confuse things
I'm going to sort of bracket that, let's count the seven days.
So he's basically on the temple grounds during עשרת ימי תשובה, aseret
yemei teshuva, right? Okay, this is when he's separated. Okay, so he
goes, he comes here to the בית המקדש. Beit Ha-mikdash. He's here
so he's not sleeping with his wife because if he sleeps with
his wife maybe he'll become a ספק נידה. sofek nida. Means that
we have to concern ourselves that the day before he came maybe
that scenario happened. Okay, so the day before he came that scenario
happened if on day zero, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah again I guess,
he if he were בא ונידל ba ve-nidal on that day right
if he were then when would he be then and he's going
to the מקווה mikvah let's say every single day, they're even doing
the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Aduma etc. But what would
his day seven be if he got that status here? This would
be his day seven right of the time that he was you
know that he became טמא tameh if that had actually occurred. Okay.
So now if he were like a נידה nida when would he
go to the מקווה mikvah if that were his day seven? That
night. Okay, that night means the night prior to day seven. When
would he become totally wait a minute that actually does work one
minute
if he's then day the day that he separated was day one?
One minute.
Oh no no no you're right that's the point I'm sorry thank
you thank you very much Michael. That's the point. Yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah thank you thank you thank you. Okay. The concern is
that he had sex you know a minute before coming to the
בית המקדש Beit Ha-mikdash okay so he came to the בית המקדש
Beit Ha-mikdash let's say that he showed up here at noon maybe
he had sex with his wife at 11:00 at 11:00 a.m. So
thank you Mike so then this is day seven, day seven is
day seven if he became if he actually was טמא tameh when
when he came to the בית המקדש Beit Ha-mikdash and had sex
with his wife right before. This is day seven. He goes to
if he was like a נידה nida he would go to the
מקווה mikvah the night of the seven the night going into the
going basically the night of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Right. And then
he wouldn't be 100% totally טהור tahor until מוצאי יום כיפור motzaei
Yom Kippur because he would need another nightfall. So he says אה
ah but if he's allowed to go the day of the seven
and he goes to the מקווה mikvah here then when it becomes
the night night of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that's the הערב שמש
ha'arev shemesh and therefore he's totally טהור tahor and allowed to serve
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So he says, you see that
if that's our concern, then the only way this works is if
he can go to the מקווה mikvah the day of the seventh
and not the night of the seventh.
Just to be clear about the language we're using like a shortcut,
it's all that ספק נדה safek niddah situation.
Yeah. Right.
And it didn't say, and it didn't say we tell him, like
they tell you, like they tell you if you're about to have
some tests in the morning, no food and drink the night before
whatever, don't have sex with your wife the night before. No. Once
we're concerned, we'll have to be concerned about worst case scenario and
he became a בועל נדה boel niddah minute before showing up. So
that's true, the only way it's going to be solved is if
he can go to the מקווה mikvah on the day of the
seventh.
Have we seen anybody say what the name of this לשכה lishka
means?
No, we're going to get to that. Okay. אלא לאו שמע מינה,
Ella lav shema mina, so from this you can infer if that's
our concern that בועל נדה אינו כנדה, boel niddah eino ke-niddah, that
he's not like a נדה niddah and he can go the day
of the seventh, he doesn't have to go the night of the
seventh. Now a lot of the people that go to the מקווה,
mikvah, the basic assumption is you go during the day and you
can go even the day you become טמא. tamei. And it's interesting,
I mean the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell out what would be the
logic if the Torah says he has the same טומאה, tumah, then
what would be the logic to allow him to go earlier? But
if the reason that a נדה niddah waits till the night of
the seventh, what's connected and some מפרשים meforshim say this, to an
assumption that she might be bleeding or having her menstruation for a
full seven days, then it's a very fascinating logic the גמרא Gemara
could be suggesting. As a seven day טומאה, tumah, he's allowed to
go to the מקווה mikvah during the daytime. We have other seven
day טומאות tumahs where somebody goes to the מקווה mikvah daytime. A
woman who's a זבה zavah who's טמאה tmeiah seven days goes to
the מקווה mikvah the day of the seventh. A man or a
woman who's טמא tamei by contact with a מת, meis, right, they
do the sprinkling of the ashes or whatever, that's the day of
the seventh, it's not the night after, it's not full seven days.
So as a טומאה, tumah, maybe he can go the day of
the seventh. Maybe the only reason the woman doesn't go in the
day is because of the concern of that the menstruation has not
yet ended, a Torah concern, not a rabbinic concern, but the idea
that the menstruation could be lasting throughout the day of the seventh.
So he has the טומאה tumah without the menstruation, so maybe he
goes the day of the seventh, which actually is the pattern for
normal טומאות tumahs of seven days. So I just like it as
a conceptual model. So that's what he's arguing. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אלא לאו שמע מינה בועל נדה אינו כנדה. Ella
lav shema mina boel niddah eino ke-niddah. רב שימי מנהרדעא אמר, Rav
Shimi mi-Neharde'a amar, רב שימי Rav Shimi from נהרדעא Neharde'a says: אפילו
תימא בועל נדה כנדה, Afilu teima boel niddah ke-niddah, no,
he might be like a נדה niddah and goes the night of
the seventh. How about this concern? דמפרישין ליה שעה אחת סמוך לשקיעת
החמה, De-mafrishin lei sha'ah achas samuch le-shki'as ha-chamah,
that basically you get him to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash not
noon on day one, you get him to the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash a minute before sunset on day zero. So on the second
day ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah here, before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is
over, you have him right before sunset at the end of the
second day ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah come to the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. So if he's had sex recently with his wife, the last
moment was actually
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, would not have had a chance on day
one. So he's really seven full days and a minute in the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but he doesn't come in the middle of
day one, he comes right before day one begins. Okay. So now
we're going to discuss this issue, although you can't prove it from
our scenario, what is the story of a בועל נדה? boel niddah?
Does he go to the מקווה mikvah on the day or the
night of the seventh? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתבי.
Meitvei. I'll ask you on your position that it's the day. כל
חייבי טבילות טבילתן ביום, Kol chayavei tvilos tvilosan ba-yom,
anybody who's obligated in טבילות tvilos to go to the מקווה mikvah
goes in the day. Like I said, that is the standard that
טבילה tvila is in the
day. נדה ויולדת, Niddah ve-yoledes, the only exception is a נדה, niddah,
a woman who's a נדה niddah and who has had her menstruation
and a woman who has given birth. טבילתן בלילה. Tvilosan ba-laylah. They
are the only ones because the Torah links the טומאה tumah of
childbirth to the טומאה tumah of נדה. niddah. Those are the only
ones that wait the full seven days and go at night, do
not go the day of the seventh. So the גמרא Gemara says
that sounds like נדה niddah in, בועל נדה לא. boel niddah lo.
It says נדה, niddah, the only exceptions are נדה niddah and יולדת.
yoledes. So presumably בועל נדה boel niddah would not be an exception
and he would go the day of the seventh. So that would
be a proof to רב זירא Rav Zeira and a challenge to
those that would argue with רב זירא. Rav Zeira. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, that's not
a proof. לא, Lo, נדה וכל דאתי מריבוי. niddah ve-chol de-asi mi-ribui.
No, נדה niddah means a נדה niddah and everybody that falls into
the chapter of נדה. niddah. So this man comes, his טומאה tumah
is that of a נדה, niddah, so that would be included in
the word נדה. niddah. So you cannot make a big deal that
בועל נדה boel niddah wasn't mentioned there. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara is going to try again. מיתבי. Meitvei. בעל קרי כמגע שרץ.
Ba'al keri ke-maga sheretz. We have a ברייתא braisa that says, excuse
me, a משנה Mishnah in זבים Zavim that says, a man who
has seminal emission is like somebody who touched a שרץ. sheretz. Touched
a dead rodent. Which means what? Which means that he is
a ראשון לטומאה. rishon le-tumah. Okay, his level of טומאה tumah is
that not as a source of טומאה tumah but as a ראשון
rishon and therefore he can only make let's say food טמא, tamei,
he can't make people or vessels טמא. tamei. So that's like, he's
like a שרץ. sheretz. Touched a שרץ, sheretz, he's also
like
somebody. same הלכות *Halachos*. They are a טומאה tumah *Tumah* of a
man who touched a dead body. A מת meis *Meit* is called
not an אב הטומאה av hatumah. *Av Hatumah*, but an אבי אבות
הטומאה *Avi Avot Hatumah*, like a granddaddy of טומאות tumot. *Tumot*. Because
if you touch a מת *Meit*, your status is not a ראשון
rishon, *Rishon*, which it normally is when you touch something טמא tamei,
*Tamei*, but it's an אב av. *Av*. You are have a full
status of an אב av. *Av*, and that's why seven days and
the whole thing etc. So number one, somebody who touches a dead
body is an אב av הטומאה *Av Hatumah*. Number two, it's a
seven-day טומאה tumah *Tumah*. And therefore, a בא אל נדה niddah *Bo
El Nidah*, a man who's had sex with a woman who's a
נדה niddah *Nidah*, fits into that category: אב הטומאה *Av Hatumah* and
seven days. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, but if that's
the category you're putting him in, when does a person who's טמא
tamei. *Tamei* because of a dead body have his טהרה *Tahara* process?
Day of the seventh, not the following night. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, מאי לאו לטבילה *Mai lav litvilah*, is it not making
this comparison for טבילה *Tvilah* purposes and saying that you know that
here you go, both you know, both of these people, the man
who touches the dead body and the man who has had sex
with a woman who's a נדה niddah *Nidah*, both go to the
מקוה mikvah, *Mikvah* the day of the seventh? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, לא לטומאתן *Lo letumatan*, no, it means the טומאה tumah
*Tumah*, one-day טומאה tumah. *Tumah* or seven-day טומאה tumah, *Tumah*. We're not
making comparisons about when you would go to the מקוה mikvah. *Mikvah*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, טומאתן בהדיא כתיב הוא *Tumatan behadya
ketiva hu*. You don't need a משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* to tell me
that. The תורה Torah *Torah* tells me that. It says that the
first two are one-day טומאות tumot *Tumot*, the last two are seven-day
טומאות *Tumot*. האי טומאת שבעה כתיב ביה והאי טומאת שבעה כתיב ביה
*Hai tumat shivah ketiva beh vehai tumat shivah ketiva beh*. By both
cases, both the contact of the dead body and this man who
has had sex with his wife when she was a נדה niddah,
*Nidah*, both of them the תורה *Torah* says it's seven days. You
do not need a משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, does not need to put
them in the same category. If the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* is putting
them in the same category, it is to tell me more than
that. It is to tell me that they both go to the
מקוה mikvah. *Mikvah*, you know, in the daytime. That's what the argument
is. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא לאו לטבילתן *Ella lav
litvilatan*. So again, if it's telling me something interesting, it must be
telling me that טבילה *Tvilah* is during the day. So that is
the support to רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*. גמרא *Gemara* says, לא *Lo*,
not necessarily. לעולם לטומאתן *Le'olam letumatan*. I'll tell you that really the
point is just to say one day or seven days and nothing
in—it's not saying anything interesting of when they go to the מקוה
mikvah *Mikvah*. So סיפא איצטריכא ליה *Seifa itztericha leh*. And you know
what? You're right. The first part of the משנה *Mishnah* is superfluous.
The first part of the משנה *Mishnah* is just restating what's already
explicit in the תורה *Torah*. So why was it taught? To get
you to the second part of the משנה *Mishnah*. What's the second
part of the משנה *Mishnah*? Here's the second part of the משנה
*Mishnah*: אלא שחמורה ממנו בא אל נדה niddah *Ella shechamura mimenu bo
el nidah*, a man who's had sex with a woman when she
was a נדה niddah *Nidah* has one aspect that he's more strict
than a man who came in contact with a dead body. What's
that, or a woman who came in contact with a dead body?
What's the way he's more strict? שמטמא משכב mishkav ומושב בטומאה קלה
betumah kallah, לטמא אוכלין ומשקין letamei ochlin umashkin *Shemetamei mishkav umoshav betumah
kalah letamei ochlin umashkin*. One of the whole special הלכות *Halachos* about
people who have טומאה tumah *Tumah* because of things that have happened
to their body or things that came out of their body, basically
a woman who's a נדה *Nidah* because of menstruation or who bleed
not during her normal cycle, or a man who's a זב zav,
*Zav*, right, which is because of something, some penile emission. All of
those cases in the תורה *Torah*, you know, the תורה *Torah* gives
a lot of airtime to those cases in תזריע מצורע *Tazria-Metzora*. So
all of those cases it says any seat that they sit on
will be טמא tamei. *Tamei*. This is the טומאה tumah. *Tumah* of
משכב mishkav ומושב *Mishkav umoshav*. And that is actually a very special
category in two ways. Number one is it becomes טמא tamei *Tamei*
even if they don't touch it, just by virtue of it having
been their seat. So if you imagine, like, you know, the princess
and the pea, you have ten pillows stacked on one another, all
of those pillows, no matter how distant they are from him and
from his touch or her, you know, all those pillows are the
seat of the זב *Zav* or the זבה zavah, *Zavah* and they're
all טמא tamei. *Tamei*. Number one, it doesn't need touch. And number
two is it's an אב הטומאה *Av Hatumah*. By being defined as
the seat of a זב *Zav* or זבה *Zavah*, it is not
one degree lower, a ראשון rishon *Rishon*, it actually is an אב
הטומאה *Av Hatumah*, a source of טומאה tumah *Tumah*.
Even if the person had not touched the מטה *Mita* since becoming
a זב *Zav*?
Yeah, exactly. No contact, it's just weight was supported on it. He
sat on it or sat once
in his life?
No, no, no, no. After he became a זב *Zav*, but he
doesn't have to touch it, he has to sit on it. Okay,
so he could sit on it without touching it, right? You could
sit on, you know, ten mattresses stacked on one another and every
single mattress, you know,
anything
that is supporting his weight is his seat or her seat and
therefore is a משכב mishkav *Mishkav*, called a משכב *Mishkav* or a
מושב moshav, *Moshav*, and therefore it's a seven-day טומאה tumah *Tumah*. It
doesn't need contact, it needs to be sat on, doesn't need contact,
and is an אב הטומאה *Av Hatumah*. Now, so בא אל נדה
*Bo El Nidah*, that's only true about these טומאות *Tumot* that things
that come from the body. If a man touches or woman touched
a dead body, even though it's a seven-day טומאה tumah *Tumah* and
it's very strict, you need the sprinkling of the ashes of the
פרה אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah*, it has all these other stringencies,
it does not have this status of seat, that if that man
or woman sits on something that that status is somehow a special
status. So what the משנה says is, this is one way in
which the man who had sex with a נדה is stricter than
somebody who touches a corpse, which is that he because he gets
the טומאה tumah of the woman he slept with, he actually also
makes a משכב and a מושב, moshav okay? And that does not
apply to the man who touched a corpse. So that's the basic
point. The משנה is not coming to tell you when they go
to the מקוה, it's leading up to pointing out ways in which,
you know, one category, one of these people is more strict than
the other. And the way in which the man who sleeps with
a woman who is a נדה is more strict than the person
who touches a corpse is that the man who sleeps with her
gets her טומאה tumah to the effect that even he makes a
משכב and מושב moshav even without touching it. Now, there is one
difference because he's a very interesting middle category, like the possibility that
he has seven days but he can go in the day. The
middle category is, when he sits on something, again, even if he
doesn't touch it, it doesn't become an אב הטומאה. It only becomes
a ראשון לטומאה. rishon letumah. So again, since he does not actually
have the things happening to his body, he just got the טומאה
tumah transferred to him, you know, or extended to him, he makes
a משכב and מושב but without making it an אב. So let
me just read you those words,
אלא שחמור ממנו בועל נדה, ella shechamur mimennu boel niddah, more strict
than the person who touches a corpse, because this person שמתמא משכב
ומושב, shemetamei mishkav umoshav, he makes seats and, you know, and whatever
and things you sleep on, things you sit on, טמא, tamei again,
even without touching. With touching it's not a חידוש, chiddush, even without
touching, בטומאה b'tumah. קלה, but there's this way he actually is also
different from the נדה that it's only a lighter טומאה. tumah It's
a ראשון, not an אב. לטמא אוכלין ומשקין and a ראשון can
only make food and liquid טמא. tamei If you're only an אב
can make a person and vessels טמא. tamei Okay, so that's the
reason it's quoted, it's to point out this difference, but you cannot
argue anything from the question about when he goes to the מקוה.
Yes, Michael?
I just have a quick question. This always has to be בדיעבד,
bedieved, right? Because if we're really worried about that and forgetting a
little bit, like doesn't the ציץ tzitz take care of some of
this stuff? Like in other words, you know, like...
well what would be בדיעבד? bedieved? So we'll get to that in
a minute. Okay, so hold on. So the גמרא is not done
with this question about when a בועל נדה boel niddah goes to
the מקוה. תא שמע ta shema come hear. דתניא דבי חייא, detanya
devei Chiyya, we have a ברייתא. braita. הזב והזבה והמצורע והמצורעת, hazzav
vehazzavah vehametzora vehametzora'at, הזב והזבה, hazzav vehazzavah, a
man or woman with these different types of flows which are seven
day טומאה, tumah or a man or woman who has צרעת, tzara'at,
ובועל נדה uvowel niddah and a man who's had sex with a
נדה, וטמא מת utmei meit and somebody who became טמא tamei, through
the contact with a dead body, all these are seven day טומאות.
טבילתן ביום, tevilitan bayom, they all go in the day. So רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya says black and white, בועל נדה boel niddah goes
during the day. Every seven day טומאה tumah goes during the day
with the one exception of נדה ויולדת, niddah veyoledet, טבילתן בלילה. tevilitan
balaylah. Okay, that's the one exception. So it spelled out what was
implicit in the previous משנה. Very clearly בועל נדה boel niddah goes
into the day. דייקא, dayka, that is an absolute contradiction to the
one who challenged רב זירא. Rav Zeira. It's funny that it frames
it as a challenge because in the end רב זירא Rav Zeira
was the one who said this and now everything has supported רב
זירא. Rav Zeira. So at the end of the day, the challengers
have been defeated and רב זירא's Rav Zeira's position stands that the
בועל נדה boel niddah goes, can go during the day, which means
that the כהן kohen can come to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
day one. He doesn't have to come the night before and then
even if he had sex a minute before with his wife, day
seven is day seven, goes to the מקוה by nightfall by יום
כיפור Yom Kippur he will be totally טהור. tahor. Okay, so that's
why we had that discussion of בועל נדה. boel niddah. Now, let's
take a look at Michael's question about why are we so hyper
concerned about a possible טומאה. tumah So that's exactly where the גמרא
now turns.
דעד שתהא מפרישו מטומאת ביתו, dead shetehei mafrisho mitumat beito, you're so
afraid if his wife is with him oh my god who knows
what happens, she'll have sex and she'll be a נדה and that's
your
concerns. תפרישו מטומאת מת, tefrisho mitumat meit, you should make sure that
he doesn't ever come in contact with any other human being during
those seven days, because if he's in contact with another person, maybe
the person will die on him and he'll be טמא מת. tmei
meit. So I
mean, you know, once these are your concerns, like, you know, it's
sort of like the משנה אין לדבר סוף. ein ladavar sof. So
the גמרא says, אמר רב תחליפא אבוה דרב הונא משמיה דרבא, amar
Rav Tachlifa avuha deRav Huna mishmei deRava, זאת אומרת, zot omeret, from
the fact that we're not concerned with that, this teaches you, טומאת
מת הותרה היא בציבור, tumat meit hutrah hi betzibbur, that actually, right,
that we are not concerned about טומאת מת. tumat meit. As you
know, as we learned in פסחים, Psachim, there's a general principle that
if the כהנים, kohanim, the בעלים, ba'alim, the question of exactly who,
but let's say the כהנים kohanim are טמאים tme'im and it's a
קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, especially or more particularly it's a קרבן korban
that has a fixed time and has to be brought today, you
bring it even though everybody is טמא. tamei, Okay, but the question
is, is the concept like טומאה tumah, doesn't apply in that case
or yes, it does apply, it is a problem, but the problem
is being
overruled. The idea that yes you are actually bringing a קרבן בטומאה
korban b'tumah and that is problematic but we're going to allow it
to happen, that's the idea of דחויה. dchuya. There's a problem but
we're overriding the problem. So if your adoption if your principle is
טומאה הותרה, tumah hutra, it's like there's no prohibition at all then
or no you know no problematic at all, then you don't have
to work so hard to avoid it. Okay so he's saying why
are we not avoiding working to avoid a guy dropping dead on
him? Because טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutra b'tzibur and therefore if it
happens you're not even doing anything wrong and therefore we don't have
to work so hard to avoid it. So then the question is
why separate him from his wife? Because the only טומאה tumah. that's
הותרה בציבור hutra b'tzibur is טומאת מת tumat meit or טומאה tumah,
of contact with other things. טומאה of a status of a personal
status like נידה, niddah, זב, זבה, and בועל נידה, boel niddah, which
is not about just physical contact it's more about personal status, those
טומאות are not הותרה בציבור. hutra b'tzibur.
So what about we tell the entire population of כהנים גדולים kohanim
gdolim at the same time?
Because exactly the entire population of the subset the null set the
set consisting of one. So yes and also ציבור tzibur also reflects
the קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. Now again it's not you could you
could discuss and רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot discuss this is the
קרבן korban of יום כיפור Yom Kippur a קרבן ציבור? korban tzibur?
You know there's the קרבן korban that he brings for כלל ישראל,
klal Yisrael, that's a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, but there's also his
personal קרבן. korban. Okay now but of course that's necessary sort of
to allow to have everything take place and also as I told
you a lot in פסחים, Psachim, it's not just the status of
a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, it's really any fixed time קרבן, korban,
so even if you do not consider his personal קרבן korban to
be a ציבור קרבן, tzibur korban, it's a קרבן korban that has
to be done today. And therefore and he's the only one to
do it. So basically the answer is yeah you know what we're
not so worried about טמאי מת, tmei meit, let him be טמאי
מת tmei meit big deal he has he has to be bringing
the קרבן korban today, it's a fixed time, it's קרבן ציבור, korban
tzibur, so big deal we're not going to be concerned about that.
But what we will be concerned about is a טומאה that will
not be will not be הותרה hutra and will will be a
problem which is the טומאה of בועל נידה. boel niddah. That's his
answer. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina comes back and says אפילו
תימא טומאת המת דחויה afillu teima tumat hameit dchuya
and again the keyword here is המת, hameit, okay because טומאת נידה
tumat niddah and בועל נידה boel niddah is never overwritten, okay but
the טומאת מת tumat meit is. אפילו תימא טומאת מת דחויה היא
בציבור, afillu teima tumat meit dchuya hi b'tzibur, even if טומאת מת
tumat meit is only pushed off meaning it's overwritten but it's still
problematic and we would therefore work to avoid it. So if we
would work to avoid טומאת מת tumat meit why do we let
him come in contact with other human beings? טומאת המת לא שכיחא.
tumat hameit lo shechicha. טומאת מת לא שכיחא. tumat meit lo shechicha.
You know it's just a question of percentage, there's a question of
numbers. Somebody dropping dead on you is a little less likely than
his wife becoming a נידה niddah and you know even if it's
not normally her menstrual period. Okay but those things happen. So we're
not going to be afraid somebody is going to drop dead on
you even if we are working to avoid טומאת מת. tumat meit.
Now you will remember by the way that we do part of
the process which we haven't mentioned yet is that the entire seven
days they sprinkle on him the ashes of the פרה אדומה which
is all a concern of טומאת מת. tumat meit. So we're going
to have to when we get to that again raise but if
it's טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutra b'tzibur why are we even bothering?
Okay so now we're going to look at that question of whether
טומאה is הותרה בציבור hutra b'tzibur or דחויה בציבור. dchuya b'tzibur. Let's
take a look. So and again it will apply to the כהן
גדול. kohen gadol. ציבור tzibur might not meaning that the ציבור tzibur
is טמא tamei, sometimes it means the ציבור tzibur is טמא tamei,
but anyway for here we'll say because like by the פסח Pesach
where those are the ones who are bringing the קרבן korban but
anyway no the the basic meaning is of a קרבן ציבור. korban
tzibur. And again as רש"י Rashi says you know and תוספות Tosafot
says even he even if there's the כהן kohen's personal קרבן korban
is not a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, it still is קבוע לו
זמן kavuah lo zman and therefore we'll have the idea that it
could be brought even בטומאה. be'tumah So that's the question. So in
those circumstances do we just like ignore טומאה or we override it?
So let's take a look. איתמר, itmar, it was said, טומאת המת
tumat hameit when the טומאה again corpse טומאה or contact טומאה, these
are the only things that are that you override or you allow
you know for a קרבן. korban. So רב נחמן אמר הותרה היא
בציבור, Rav Nachman amar hutra hi b'tzibur, it's completely permissible, it's not
even a problem, okay once you're dealing with a קרבן ציבור. korban
tzibur. ורב ששת אמר דחויה היא בציבור, v'Rav Sheshet amar dchuya hi
b'tzibur, no it's a problem we override it but we're still problematic.
So now what would be a נפקא מינה nafka mina between הותרה
hutra and דחויה? dchuya? So it says like this היכי
דאיכא טמאי וטהורין בהוא בית אב, heichi d'ika tmei u'tehorin b'hahu beit
av, so forget forget the issue of of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It's basically it's Monday. Okay it's Monday and
everybody of the כהנים kohanim who it's Monday on ו' חשון Vov
Cheshvan and any all the כהנים kohanim though whose date of to
work it is that day that's the בית אב, beit av, right?
It's the subsection the subgroup of the כהנים kohanim that work the
week, the משמר, mishmar, this is the group of those כהנים kohanim
from the משמר mishmar that work are working on Monday and it
just so happens that all of those כהנים kohanim became טמא tamei
okay that בית אב. beit av. So that's problem. The כהנים kohanim
who now theoretically you could find in another כהן, Kohen, but the
כהנים Kohanim whose job it is to work today are all טמא,
tamei, and you have a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur to bring today
on ו' חשון. Vav Cheshvan. What's the קרבן ציבור korban tzibur you
bring on Monday ו' חשון? Vav Cheshvan? The same one you bring
every day, the תמיד. Tamid. Okay, so you've got a תמיד Tamid
to bring, the כהנים Kohanim of that day are טמא, tamei what
do you do? Let's take a look. Okay,
so it goes like this. היכא דאיכא טמא וטהור בהאי בית אב,
Heicha de'ika tamei v'tahor b'hai beis av, if the כהנים Kohanim of
that day have some טמא, tamei some טהור, tahor, and you have
to bring your תמיד, Tamid, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דטהורים עדיפי טמא
לא עדיפי. kulei alma lo peligi d'tahorim adifei tamei lo adifei. Nobody
would say you would just say pshhh, nothing, let the טמאים tme'im
do it. If you have an easy choice to go with the
טהורים, tehorim, even if you say הותרה, hutra, you're going to go
with the טהורים. tehorim. Okay, כי פליגי, ki peligi, when is there
a debate? להדורי לאתויי טהורים מבית אב אחרינא, L'aduray l'asuyei tahorim m'beis
av achrina, that all of the Monday כהנים Kohanim are טמאים. tme'im.
Okay, but you know, you have the כהנים Kohanim of this week
that are right here, they came to ירושלים Yerushalayim for this week.
All we'll have to do is ring them up, like when you
know, and say, hey, we need a few guys, can you get
a few כהנים Kohanim to come because all the Monday כהנים Kohanim
are טמאים? tme'im? Do you bother with that little effort of ringing
up the כהנים Kohanim that are here, you know, waiting to serve
this week but not today, and have them come to the בית
המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? להדורי לאתויי טהורים מבית אב אחרינא, L'aduray l'asuyei tahorim
m'beis av achrina, to do the effort to get כהנים Kohanim from
another day's from another day. רב נחמן אמר הותרה היא בציבור, Rav
Nachman amar hutra hi b'tzibur, it's completely permissible, and therefore לא מהדרינן,
lo mahadrinan, you don't even bother even if there's another כהן Kohen
standing there, you know what, it's not his day. Okay, big deal,
everybody's טמא, tamei. it's not a problem, it's a קרבן ציבור. korban
tzibur. רב ששת אמר דחויה היא בציבור. Rav Sheshes amar dchuyah hi
b'tzibur. No, it's a problematic situation, we'll override it if we have
no choice, but we have a choice. Okay, ומהדרינן, u'mahadrinan, and we
would try to find another כהן Kohen who could do the עבודה.
avodah Okay, that's very reasonable debate. Now the גמרא wants to make
it more extreme.
When you ignore it, as the word ignore bothers me for מתיר,
matir, right? In other words, if you ignore something, you're still acknowledging
that it's חל. chal.
Okay, but it doesn't mean that there's no טומאה. Maybe an interesting
comparison would be the question which gets debated in the אחרונים acharonim
of how we think about פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh on שבת, Shabbos,
הותרה hutra or דחויה. dchuyah. So if I asked you, if somebody
goes ahead and is driving somebody to the hospital, פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh on שבת, Shabbos, are they מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos but they
have a מצוה mitzvah to be מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbos, or it's
not חילול שבת? chillul Shabbos? Saving a life on שבת Shabbos is
not חילול שבת? chillul Shabbos? So that's the question.
Okay, a huge difference.
Right, so that's the difference between הותרה hutra and דחויה. dchuyah. Right,
are they basically violating the laws of a קרבן korban brought בטומאה
be'tumah. but they're allowed to violate it? Or no, they're not violating.
For קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, there's no law that you can't bring
it בטומאה. Okay, so that's what I mean when I say ignore.
No violation is הותרה. hutra.
הותרה, hutra, right, no
violation.
Wait a minute, if they're saying you don't have to מחלל שבת
mechalel Shabbos and don't try, so why can't you just bring up
the כהנים Kohanim from the tomorrow?
Okay, so that's exactly the question about. So let's take a look.
The גמרא now has another version of this debate. איכא דאמרי, Ika
d'amri, some say, אפילו היכא דאיכא טהורים וטמאים בהאי בית אב פליגי.
afillu heicha de'ika tehorim v'tme'im b'hai beis av peligi. Now that's really
a real extreme of the הותרה. hutra. There's absolutely no prohibition of
bringing a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur with כהנים Kohanim who are טמאים,
tme'im, not just when you have to. There's no prohibition. So even
if there are טמאים tme'im and טהור tahor כהנים Kohanim in this
בית אב, beis av, you can have the טמא כהנים Kohanim feel
bad, they have to sit out because they're טמא, they can't work
today, and today on Monday whatever ו' חשון, Vav Cheshvan, they can't
work. But they don't worry. When it comes time for the תמיד,
Tamid, we'll call you up, you can work because there's no problem
of טמא כהנים Kohanim bringing a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur.
That's taking it out of the polarity between the two.
I understand, that's an extreme idea of הותרה. hutra. There's absolutely no
problem, the prohibitions in the תורה that a טמא כהן Kohen cannot
do the עבודה were not said by קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. It's
a real extreme. רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, okay,
בהאי בית אב פליגי. b'hai beis av peligi. They debate, רב נחמן
Rav Nachman and רב ששת. Rav Sheshes. רב נחמן Rav Nachman disagrees.
ואמר עבדי נמי טמאים, V'amar avidie nami tame'im, they can even do
it even if there's an even if the other כהנים Kohanim waiting
to do it who are טהור. tahor. Big deal, it's a קרבן
ציבור, korban tzibur, you can do it with a טמא. It's a
really extreme position. דכל טומאת מת בציבור רחמנא שריא, De'kol tumas meis
b'tzibur rachmana sharya, any טומאת מת tumas meis is completely permissible, it's
not overriding, there is no prohibition. And again though, this is a
contact טומאה, טומאת מת, tumas meis, it does not apply to נדה
or בועל נדה, bo'el niddah, and that's why we obviously have to
be, you know, clearly it's a concern about the בועל נדה bo'el
niddah whether the מת is a concern, הותרה hutra or דחויה, dchuyah,
and how much are we going to be concerned about טומאת מת,
tumas meis, that's part of this debate. Before we end today, I
wanted to point your attention to an interesting discussion in תוספות Tosfos
because I keep on telling you that it's not just about קרבן
ציבור, korban tzibur, it's about a קרבן korban that has to be
done today. Is there ever a special like the כהן גדול's Kohen
Gadol own קרבן? korban? Is there ever a special status of קרבן
ציבור? korban tzibur? So look at the very end of the final
He says that it might make a difference exactly this question. He
says like this. He says,
I'm going to tell you.
It is one, two, three, about one, two, three, six lines before
it ends, it starts with word למימר. lemaimar. Okay, so one word
in. People see where I'm reading from? It says מיהי דפסח, mihi
dipasach, even though it comes בכנופיא, bichnufya, because this whole question whether
פסח Pesach is considered a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, because it's not
brought for כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael as a corporate entity, it's just
every single individual brought it. So it comes בכנופיא, bichnufya, with a
group, en masse, חשיב כקרבן ציבור, chashiv k'korban tzibur, it's like a
קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, ודוחה את השבת ואת הטומאה. v'docheh es haShabbos
v'es hatumah. מכל מקום, Mikol makom, כיון דלאו כולהו מייתי חד פסח
בשותפות, keivan delav kulhu meisi chad Pesach b'shutfus,
it's not one קרבן korban being brought for all of them as
a corporate entity. Next, so it's merely not a real קרבן ציבור,
korban tzibur, מהדרינן אטהורין, maadrinan atahorin, everybody would agree we would try
to find טהור tahor people to bring it. אפילו מאן דאמר טומאה
היתרא היא בקרבן ציבור גמור, Afilu man deamar tumah heitra hi b'korban
tzibur gamur, הבא בשותפות. haba b'shutfus.
The discussion here is a real קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, a קרבן
korban brought for כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, things that are a fixed
time but not a real קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, like קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach or maybe אהרן's Aharon קרבן, korban, that might override, but
everybody would agree that's in the דחויה duchuya category, not in the
הותרה hutra category. דכן משמע לקמן בסמוך דאלו של אהרן, D'chein mashma
lekaman b'samuch d'eilu shel Aharon, אהרן's Aharon ram, אף על גב דזימנא
קביעא ליה, af al gav d'zimna kveia lei, it has a fixed
time, ודחי את השבת ואת הטומאה v'dachi es haShabbos v'es hatumah כקרבן
ציבור, k'korban tzibur, מכל מקום, mikol makom, כיון דקרבן יחיד הוא, keivan
d'korban yachid hu, it's at the end of the day it's a
personal קרבן, korban, מהדרינן אטהורין לכולי עלמא, maadrinan atahorin l'chulei alma,
everybody would agree you'd try to get טהור tahor people. So this
is a great תוספות Tosfos because often we talk about טומאה הותרה
בציבור, tumah hutra b'tzibur, but as we know, it really is about
a fixed time קרבן korban overrides regardless. But תוספות Tosfos says here's
the difference. Okay, when it's a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, that's when
you can have an extreme position of complete הותרה hutra and we
won't even bother to look for טהור tahor people, completely הותרה. hutra.
When it's a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid, even a קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, but it's not a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, it's a קרבן
יחיד korban yachid with a fixed time, then everybody agrees, even if
you say some version of הותרה, hutra, everybody would agree there that
at least we would try to get טהורין tahorin to bring it.
So קרבן ציבור korban tzibur does remain at a higher level than
a fixed time קרבן korban that is a קרבן יחיד korban yachid
in terms of this issue of overriding and must be done. Okay,
so we will end with that
for today.